<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>grapevine on Aymeric Roucher</title>
        <link>https://a-roucher.github.io/tags/grapevine/</link>
        <description>Recent content in grapevine on Aymeric Roucher</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://a-roucher.github.io/tags/grapevine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Will the Bordeaux vineyards eventually dry up?</title>
        <link>https://a-roucher.github.io/p/will-the-bordeaux-vineyards-eventually-dry-up/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://a-roucher.github.io/p/will-the-bordeaux-vineyards-eventually-dry-up/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://a-roucher.github.io/p/will-the-bordeaux-vineyards-eventually-dry-up/Bordeaux-France.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Will the Bordeaux vineyards eventually dry up?" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2013 an American study led by Professor Lee Hannah made a big splash: the average temperature in Mediterranean climates increasingly exceeding the needs of the vine, large areas would become unfit for viticulture within the next 40 years. Ten years later, the temperature has risen, yet massive abandonment of vineyards is still pending. What has proven this study wrong - so far at least?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;heat-and-vines&#34;&gt;Heat and vines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between temperature and wine quality is more complex than previously thought. To better understand it, let&amp;rsquo;s go back to the very beginning of the production of a vintage: the vine cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cycle-of-the-vine&#34;&gt;The cycle of the vine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It begins like a birth, with tears: after the first warm days of spring, the vine comes out of its winter sleep, and its sap flows like tears through the wounds left by pruning. Then the buds come out of their cotton buds to start growing. It is after this budding that the frost is dangerous, because the plant lowers its defenses against the cold. At the end of May, the flowers bloom, then slowly swell into seeds. The fruit ripens and, depending on the variety, is loaded with sugar, tannins and, in the case of black grapes, anthocyanins that give them color.  When the grapes are ripe, they are harvested and the vinification begins in the cellar. If each phase takes place under clear skies, and if the vine can grow, guided by the tireless work of the winegrowers, without being ravaged by hail, frost, mildew, or by the bumper of a drunk driver leaving at great speed on the road to the Châteaux, only then can the wine be good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-ideal-weather&#34;&gt;The ideal weather&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this cycle, the ideal weather conditions change dramatically. The winter must be cold for the vine to build up its reserves; on the contrary, during the ripening period, the ideal weather is that &amp;ldquo;baking sun&amp;rdquo; sung by the soul of wine in the words of Baudelaire. This last condition is the most important one: for example, if the Cabernet-Sauvignon does not heat up, it keeps heavy aromas of green bell pepper that unbalance its bouquet. The art of winemaking cannot be summed up in temperature alone, but the study shows that the wines of the last century were on average better after hot summers.
An American economist, Orley Ashenfelter, put this relationship into an equation: he was one of the first to predict that the very hot and dry summer of 1982 would produce an excellent year. His compatriot, the young critic Robert Parker, also made this bold prediction - and he gained worldwide fame for it, as 1982 proved them right, gradually revealing itself as one of the great vintages of the century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-limits-of-the-heat-wave&#34;&gt;The limits of the heat wave&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when temperatures are too high, one cannot make good wine anymore. In Bordeaux, the summer of 2003 is an illustration of this: the intense heat wave blocked the ripening of the grape varieties - Merlot in particular - and produced overripe tannins. It was with this in mind that the 2013 study was published, which predicted a decline in our wine regions. But this study went too far in its conclusions, because it took the climate as the only force at work. At the time, a letter of protest quickly appeared, led by Professor Van Leeuwen of the Institute of Vine and Wine, which pointed out methodological errors, as well as a major omission: Lee Hannah&amp;rsquo;s study neglected the possible adaptation of production methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;rethinking-the-work-of-the-vine&#34;&gt;Rethinking the work of the vine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wine is the son of the sun and the earth, but it has had work as its midwife,&amp;rdquo; said Paul Claudel. And to adapt their methods to global warming, winemakers did not wait for scientists. Winegrowing around the world is full of new ideas, and for decades the great Bordeaux wines have been real open-air laboratories. Many practices are being tested: for example, letting grass grow in the rows increases the albedo of the soil - the radiation reflected back to the sky instead of being transformed into heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Laccave science project has been looking at adaptations to warming in vineyards and has produced &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://paca.chambres-agriculture.fr/fileadmin/user_upload/Provence-Alpes-Cote_d_Azur/020_Inst_Paca/CRA_PACA/Documents/INNOVATION_RED_2017/Projet_LACCAVE.pdf&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;a census of adaptations being tested&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pablo Almaraz, a researcher from the University of Cadiz, has shown the tangible impact of this adaptation. He studied the relationship between the quality of Bordeaux wine, reported for over a century by a Bordeaux broker, and the average temperature from April to September. He was able to obtain an estimate of the optimal temperature: we obtain the graph below, where we see that, since 1970, the increase in temperature is preceded by a progressive increase in the optimal temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://a-roucher.github.io/p/will-the-bordeaux-vineyards-eventually-dry-up/Almaraz.png&#34;
	width=&#34;1008&#34;
	height=&#34;432&#34;
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;almaraz&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;233&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;560px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value in °C of the average temperature in Bordeaux - in yellow (the continuous line is the smoothed curve) and of the calculated optimal temperature - in green, with the 95% uncertainty margins in lighter green. Graph obtained by reproducing the steps of the work of Pablo Almaraz with the Python library pymc3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, is the Bordeaux vineyard doomed to decline? It seems that the work of the vineyard - and probably also the winemaking and maturing - has been able to adapt with a tangible effect. But this is probably only time gained, before we reach the physical limits of the vine - let&amp;rsquo;s remember that the median scenario given by &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar6/wg1/downloads/report/IPCC_AR6_WGI_SPM_final.pdf&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;the latest IPCC report&lt;/a&gt; leads &lt;em&gt;very likely&lt;/em&gt; to a global temperature increase of more than 2°C by the end of the century, in particular an increase of 4°C in Europe. Temperatures above 40°C can dry out grapes and cause apoplexy. Australian and Californian vineyards are already accustomed to this damage, and France experienced it painfully in June 2019, when a record 45°C was recorded in Marsillac, drying out a third of the Hérault harvest on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other dangers intensified by warming will increasingly threaten vineyards: for example, the &amp;ldquo;taste of smoke&amp;rdquo; that we heard about in France in the summer of 2022 when smoke from the Gironde fires &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://twitter.com/meteophile/status/1549110839172599810&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;flew over the Bordeaux vineyards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, the wine industry has fully understood the threats it faces: &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://innovin.fr/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Strat%C3%A9gie-de-la-fili%C3%A8re-viticole-face-au-changement-climatique.pdf&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;a national strategy for the industry&lt;/a&gt; has been built by a partnership including the INRAE, the major agricultural research body of the French government. Among the four possible scenarios for 2050, a &amp;ldquo;nomadic&amp;rdquo; scenario, which would involve relocating vineyards, calling into question the concept of terroir. To avoid this scenario, the industry will have to rely on a number of pillars, the last of which goes back to the root of the problem: since global warming is a societal problem, and since the wine industry will be asking the government for help in the difficulties ahead, it will have to be exemplary in mitigating global warming.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
